Guide to the Walton family papers, 1730-1980 and undated, bulk 1890-1975 RL.01339
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walton family papers
1730-1980 and undated
1890-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walton family
RL.01339
4.5 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 2 oversize folders Approximately 1700 items
The papers of the Walton family comprise journals and diaries; correspondence; writings; photographic materials; clippings; and printed material. Early items pertain to the Baker family of Hingham, Massachusetts, and letters document the Walton's courtship and early marriage. Papers from the 1920s to 1948 relate to Eleanore Walton's work with societies and clubs, and as a motion picture censor in Kansas City, Missouri. The larger Loring B. Walton Series documents Walton's student days, his service as a U.S. Army officer in the American Expeditionary Force in France and Germany, 1918-1919, and his lengthy correspondence with his mother, Eleanore, and with A. Goderic A. Hodges, a British Army officer. In addition there are a few letters from authors such as Wilmon Brewer, Count Sforza, Maurice Holleaux, and Anatole France, and a poem by Edmund Wilson. Walton's involvement with Duke University as a Romance Languages faculty member is also documented to a lesser degree. Photographs and negatives are of family member portraits, Princeton and Harvard campuses, 1920, Fort Douglas, Utah, also 1920, Hingham, Massachusetts, and unidentified subjects.
Approximately 1700 items
Biographical Note
George E. Walton
1839, Dec. 25 Born in Cincinnati, Ohio to Charles and Sarah Underwood Horsey Blake Walton
1864 Graduated from Bellevue Medical College (N.Y.). Served as Assistant Surgeon in the Union Army
1865 Toured Europe to study methods of surgery and medicine
1866 Began medical practice in Cincinnati, Ohio
circa 1870 Married Marion Young of Pittsburg, Pa. Had two sons and two daughters
1880 Assumed Chair of Medicine and Surgery at Cincinnati Academy of Medicine
1880-1881 President of Cincinnati Academy of Medicine
1883 Published The Mineral Springs of the United States and Canada with Analyses and Notes on the Prominent Spas of Europe, and a List of Sea-Side Resorts (D. Appleton)
1890 Moved to DeLand, Florida area
1892, Fall Married Eleanore C. Baker in St. Augustine, Fla. Son was Loring Baker Walton
1917, June 25 Died in Terre Haute, Indiana
Eleanore Coolidge Baker Walton
1865, March 18 Born Eleanore "Nellie" Coolidge Baker in Hingham, Massachusetts to Susan L. and James Loring Baker
1880s Studied in Chicago Attended Hingham Academy (Hingham, Mass.).
1891 Moved to Florida because of illness, treated by Dr. George E. Walton
1892, Fall Married George E. Walton in St. Augustine, Fla. Son was Loring Baker Walton
circa 1898 Moved to Kansas City, Mo. and became active on the Board of the Women's and Children's Hospital, and in the Missouri Society for Crippled Children, the Women's Chamber of Commerce, the YWCA, and the 2nd District Federation of Women's Clubs for Missouri
1933, May Appointed Assistant to Film Censor for Kansas City
1938, December Appointed Film Censor for Kansas City
1948 Retired and moved to Durham, N.C.
1958, July 12 Died in Durham, N.C.
Loring Baker Walton
1893, November 17 Born in Deland, Florida to Eleanore C. and George E. Walton
1898 Moved to Kansas City, Mo. with his mother
1916 Entered Harvard University as a graduate student A.B. degree from Princeton University.
1918-1920 Served in the U.S. Army in France, Germany, and Fort Douglas, Utah
1920, November Employed by Guaranty Trust Company in New York City
1923 (?) Returned to Europe for study and travel
1924 Awarded License-en-Lettres from the Sorbonne in Paris in classical languages
1924-1929 Instructor of Romance Languages at Princeton University
1925, December Married Susanne Joseph Lindlar. Children were Loring B. Walton, Jr. and Eleanore
1929-1963 Professor of Romance Languages at Duke University
1943 Ph.D. degree from the University of Chicago
1975, February 9 Died in Durham, N.C., buried in Maplewood Cemetery
Published: Anatole France and the Greek World (Duke University Press: 1950), A Manuscript of Thais(PMLA: 1956), and Anatole France and the First World War: the Correspondence with Carlos Blacker (1962).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Nitrate negatives are closed to use; access copies are available on request.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of the Walton family were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1984-1987 by Mrs. Loring B. Walton, Loring B. Walton, and Eleanore Walton Bequaert.
Additions to the collection were received in 2003 and 2008.
Collection Overview
The Walton family papers date from 1730 to 1980, and comprise journals and diaries; incoming and outgoing correspondence; writings; postcards, photographs, albums and negatives; clippings; printed material; and genealogical information and history relating to Hingham, Massachusetts.
Small groups of early materials refer to the lives of Eleanore's father James Loring Baker and the history of Hingham, Massachusetts. Later correspondence documents the courtship and early marriage of Eleanore Coolidge Baker and George E. Walton; an 1896 diary recounts George Walton's trip to Florida by wagon. A larger series of papers and correspondence relates to Loring Baker Walton's student years, travel abroad, service in World War I, and his role as academic author and professor of Romance Languages at Duke University. Letters in this series also document Loring B. Walton's relationship with his mother Eleanore and her involvement in various societies, clubs, and employment as a film censor in Kansas City, Missouri.
Photographs, postcards, and negatives in the collection include portraits of family members; images of travel abroad in France and Hingham, Massachusetts, circa 1920s; Fort Douglas, Utah, 1920; and the campuses of Harvard and Princeton in 1920, and unidentified subjects.
Addition (03-053)(175 items, .2 lin. ft.; dated 1917-1968) comprises materials on Loring Baker Walton, and consists primarily of scholarly correspondence and materials concerning his work on Anatole France and other projects (1932-1968). Also includes his class notes from Harvard (1917-1918), and from his training and service with the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I.
Addition (08-184)(375 items, .4 lin. ft.; dated 1891-1980 and undated) contains primarily material related to Loring Baker Walton's background and service with the American Expeditionary Forces in World War I. Includes information regarding Walton family property settlements for land they owned in Germany that was damaged during WWII. There are also letters (1891-1951) for George E. and Eleanore C. Walton.
Authors, European -- Correspondence; College students; Courtship; Mothers and sons -- Correspondence; Motion pictures -- Censorship -- United States; Women -- Societies and clubs; World War, 1914-1918 -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Germany; United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence; Great Britain. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence; Fort Douglas (Utah) -- Photographs; Hingham (Mass.) -- History; Hingham (Mass.) -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Cellulose nitrate film; Diaries; Negatives (photographs); Sforza, Carlo, Conte, 1872-1952; France, Anatole, 1844-1924; Baker family; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972; Walton, Loring Baker, 1893-1975; Walton, George E. (George Edward), 1839-1917; Walton, Eleanore C. (Eleanore Coolidge), 1865-1958; Harvard University -- Photographs; Princeton University -- Photographs; Duke University -- Faculty
- George E. and Eleanore C. Walton Papers, 1730-1958
  Scope and Contents note
  Most of the earliest items pertain to Mrs. Walton's family, the Bakers, who had settled in Hingham, Massachusetts at least by the eighteenth-century. Letters to Mrs. Walton comprise a major segment of this series, including those to her from her father, James Baker, 1880-1882. Included are courtship letters from George Walton, a physician who attended Eleanore Walton while she was convalescing near Deland, Florida. Most were written from 1891-1892, after she returned to her home in Chicago. Letters from George Walton after the marriage suggest financial hardship and indicate that the couple was frequently separated from the beginning of their marriage and during the early childhood of their son Loring. After 1895, there is a gap in the correspondence.
  Also included is George Walton's 1896 diary of a trip via wagon from Indiana to Florida. Later material and correspondence in the series pertains to Eleanore Walton's work as a clubwoman and motion picture censor in Kansas City, Missouri from the 1920s to 1948, when she retired and moved to Durham, N.C. to live with her son Loring Baker Walton, who was on the faculty at Duke University.
  The papers of Loring Baker Walton, make up a separate and larger series in this collection. An extensive series of correspondence between Eleanor and her son is located there.
  - Correspondence, 1830-1949
    - Early family, 1830-1835 (Box 1)
    - James L. Baker to Eleanore, 1880-1886, undated (Box 1)
    - George to Eleanore, 1891-1895 and undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Other correspondents to Eleanore, 1887-1949 (Box 1)
  - Papers and Photographs, 1730-1958
    - Clippings, 1924-1949 and undated (Box 1)
    - Diary of trip, 1896 (Box 1)
    - Funeral preparations for Eleanore Walton, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Hingham, Massachusetts and other family material, 1730-1828 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1883-1919 and undated (Box 1)
    - General, 1865-1956 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Loring Baker Walton Papers
  Four volumes of journal entries describe Loring Walton's daily life and thought as a student, first in Kansas City, Missouri, and later at Princeton University, which he entered in 1912. The journals record campus reaction to Woodrow Wilson's election to the presidency.
  Walton was a graduate student at Harvard when he was discharged from ROTC, called to active duty in the U.S. Army, and assigned to the American Expeditionary Force in France and Germany in 1918-1919. During the war and its aftermath, Walton assembled postcards and some photographs which complement his journal entries and correspondence. Other photographs and negatives show Fort Douglas, Utah, in 1920, the campuses of Harvard and Princeton, 1920, and Hingham, Massachusetts. Negatives are closed to use; copies may be requested in advance.
  Most of the letters in this series are addressed to Loring Walton's mother, Eleanore C. Walton, with a few to his grandmother and aunt in Kansas City, Missouri. Of interest are his characterizations of civilians during the war and occupation as well as his view of political conditions. For over 30 years Walton corresponded with A. Goderic A. Hodges, a British Army officer who lost a leg while in balloon service.
  To a limited extent there is information in the series about Walton's literary and scholarly interests. A small quantity of correspondence is from figures such as philanthropist Wilmon Brewer (from Hingham, Mass.), antifascist politican and writer Count Carlo Sforza, and art historian and archaeologist Maurice Holleaux. Included is a letter written by Anatole France, which was given to Walton, and a handwritten, signed poem by Edmund Wilson. There are several draft versions of Walton's addresses or articles, mostly undated. While there are no papers or correspondence relating to Walton's study at the Sorbonne, one address refers to his living in the home of a French family and his observations of French culture and educational methods. This series also thinly documents his involvement with Duke University through the Interdenominational Church and the Erasmus Club, and his sabbatical in Europe while a member of the Department of Romance Languages.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Nitrate negatives are closed to use; copies are available on request. Please contact Rubenstein Library Research Services for assistance.
  - Diaries, 1908-1923
    - Diaries and journals, 1908-1919, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Journals, including postcards and some photographs, 1923, July (Box 2)
    - Journal, including postcards and photographs, 1923, July (Box 3)
    - Journal, including postcards, 1923 Aug., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1911-1975
    - To mother, 1913-1919, July, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - To mother, 1919-1923, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - From mother, 1911-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Brewer, Wilmon, 1958-1972 (Box 4)
    - France, Anatole, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Hodges, A. Goderic A., 1930-1975, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Holleaux, Maurice, 1932 (Box 5)
    - Sforza, Count Carlo, 1933-1950 (Box 5)
    - General, 1932-1975 (Box 5)
  - Other Papers, 1905-1967
    - Duke University, 1950-1967 (Box 5)
    - Military service, 1918-1934 (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Edmund, undated (Box 5)
    - Writings and speeches, 1905-1923 and undated (Box 5)
    - General, 1916-1929, 1963, and undated (Box 5)
  - Postcards and Photographic Materials, 1913-1948
    - Wilson's inauguration, 1913
      - Postcards and photograph (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 1919-1921, 1947-1948
      - Mounted photographs, 1919 (Box 5)
      - General staff of Third Army, U.S.A., Coblenz on Rhine, 1919 (Box 5)
      - Princeton, Harvard, Hingham, Mass., 1920 (Box 5)
      - Postcards and photographs, 1921 (Box 5)
      - Fort Douglas, Utah, 1920 (Box 6)
      - Postcards and photographs, circa 1921 (Box 6)
        Scope and Contents
        Real photographic postcards from Solesmes, France, and St. Moritz, showing cathedrals, abbey, and ski resorts. Two gelatin silver photographs show Loring B. Walton posing in skis with Paul Larwill.
      - Photograph of Romance Language Department, Duke University, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
    - Photographic negatives (NITRATE), 1920s; 172 items
      Nitrate negatives are closed to use; copies are available. Please contact Rubenstein Library Research Services before coming to use this collection.
      - Fort Douglas, Utah, 1920 (Box 7)
        Numbers 1-23
      - Princeton, Harvard, 1920 (Box 7)
        Numbers 24-56
      - Princeton, Harvard, Hingham [Mass.], 1920 (Box 7)
        Numbers 57-104
      - Unidentified subjects, 1920s?, 2 folders (Box 7)
        Numbers 105-132, 133-172
- Oversize Materials
  - George and Eleanore Walton Series, 1868 and undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Other oversize papers (Oversize-folder 2)
- Addition (2003-0053), 1917-1968; 1 box (Box Acc. 03/053, Box 1)
  Addition (03-053)(175 items, .2 lin. ft.; dated 1917-1968) comprises materials of Loring Baker Walton, and consists primarily of scholarly correspondence and materials concerning his work on Anatole France and other projects (1932-1968). Also includes his class notes from Harvard (1917-1918), and from his training and service with the American Expeditionary Forces during World War I. This addition has been given core-level processing.
- Addition (2008-0184), 1891-1980 and undated; 1 box (Box Acc. 08/184, Box 1)
  Addition (2008-0184) (375 items, .4 lin. ft.; dated 1891-1980 and undated) primarily comprises material related to Loring Baker Walton's background and service with the AEF in World War I. Includes information regarding Walton family property settlements for land they owned in Germany that was damaged during World War II. There are also letters (1891-1951) for George E. and Eleanore Coolidge Baker Walton. This addition has been given core-level processing.